all right after that rather long like
redo of doing everything as a command
let's move on to the next thing so
wouldn't it be nice if we could ask what
the person's name is Let's Make a
program that does that let's let's say I
don't know let's call it prompt
okay let's call it prompt now the
command I'm about to write can be done
as a single read command I'm kind of
doing this on purpose if you know about
it but let's make a new program again so
let's call it prompt
and let's Schmo
it so now we have a program I can do uh
user in bash I know this is crazy right
but um the sipping was so nice sorry
about that I did Schmo I did schmod plus
X it's an alias we made it last time so
oopsie EnV bash all right and you can
exit out reopen it if you want um all
right now what do we want to do we want
to say
something uh something and then we want
to read in one line of input and so the
way to do that is read and we're going
to say line
right
and uh and then we'll just Echo that
line back out all right now Shel Che is
screaming at me because I'm doing a
bunch of things that are bad so one of
the things is whenever you do whenever
you're read aligning you should do Dash
are so that backslashes will be dealt
with properly it's kind of you just have
to do that right line is a variable
that's going to be put into and then
we're going to Echo the line but to be
safe we're got to wrap it in double
quotes otherwise sh'll check will just
scream at us all right so that's our
program that's it that's all that's in
the program now we can run
prompt and we can say okay something
hello
there right and it prints it out so
let's now why would I ever make thing
like this well watch okay so let's say
let's put like that there it's like we
could actually just put a question
mark and we can say
prompt uh I'm getting ahead of myself
prompt you say oopsie why does it
putting a new line well let's not do
that um okay so let's do that let's do
it's Echo well we don't want it to do a
line return so we do DN okay now you
could do this with print F and it would
take care of the same problem um might
be better to do print up later because
we're going to put color in there yeah
spoiler so so now we have hello and put
enter right and it prints out the prompt
let's let's keep going with this let's
change it to print
F and let's actually put some other
color in here now you you can do this
with read so before we get too far along
in here Reed has another thing called p
and you can put
you know the prompt in there if you want
all right um but it doesn't do you know
Replacements and stuff um and I I'm not
a fan of that um I'm always a fan of
just putting prompting ahead of the time
and just having read only do one thing
which is read the line in this case so
let's go back to print app and now when
we have a print app we have a bunch of
things we have to do here so let's stay
I want it to be a question mark and um
you know it's prompt automatically
doesn't a print up doesn't put a command
a line a line feed unless you tell it to
so we're going to say you know just
print that out let but but I want to put
some color here right so how what do we
want to you know do we want it to be
black what do we what do we want the the
prompt to be how about how about magenta
so we put you know s
here and we can do
magenta uh which we don't have yet but
we'll we'll go ahead and add it now um
you might not know this but um term
colors term colors is a program that
just prints out the terminal colors so I
can go find them and keep them in my my
program so and I just you know filtered
it and put it in there so now we have
magenta and we we have a magenta
prompt um prompt and we have a magenta
but now the whole thing is m i don't
want the thing they're typing to be that
I want the thing they're typing to be
like gold I want it to be really fancy
right so let's do that let's put another
one in here and let's make this one
yellow
right and I I happen to know that yellow
is I think
32 so whoops so we Chang this to
yellow and now we can do that prompts
hello there wait I guess that's green
wrong one maybe it's I don't know which
one is it
term colors
whoops term
colors yellow is 33 Okay
33 all right so now when to do it
prompts hello there all right oh that's
nice but you see how it bleed the colors
bled the colors bled into it well we
need to reset and I know the reset is
zero so we'll do a zero
oops
reset and
we'll do a
reset
oopsie and so after they type their they
prompt in um we will you know print a
reset actually the reset has to come
after they type so we'll put it after
Echo uh
reset actually just another print up no
Echo Das in
reset that is like no line return and
then it's gonna it's gonna
well no we want that we definitely want
that so prompts hello there enter and
then it prints out the word okay why do
we want the word to print at the
end why do we want the word to print at
the
end
um so
we're going to use a trick
here yeah we're going to use a
trick and we're going to actually do
something different we're going to
say
um see if this works I don't this might
not
work I want to try it first let's try it
first we're going to print uh
two we're going to print um one goes to
at two and you're like what the hell is
up with
that and I I want to I want to show you
this so I it might not it might not work
typical human behavior I don't know
prompt
hello all right now
so okay it's a trick I did a trick I'm
doing a trick and I want to show you why
I'm doing a trick it looks the same it's
not it's not the same let me show you
why because the output from this
is going someplace
else what does that even
mean why ises that a
thing because watch what happens if I
say let's say I want to
say uh
hello
whoops hello
prompt
uh right like what is that going to
do rob you see what it
did like think about this for a second
if you don't know what
happened okay so why did it print my
name out
properly right so
now if I hadn't done that yeah watch if
I don't put the redirect there what's it
going to
do now what's it going to
do
nothing you see what it
did I want you to pause the video and
understand what just happened okay there
are two streams of output in bash or
anything really and one of them is
standard error and that's kind of throwa
away and we regularly redirect that to
devnull and things like that and the
other one is standard output and that is
significant standard output is something
you should always use you should always
capture and printing error code and
informational logging and all that stuff
to standard error is a bad practice it's
an anti-pattern so don't do it and in
this case the prompting to to get
something new went to standard error and
so we were able to get that and we did a
we did a thing here this is the first
time you've ever understood anything
about redirecting standard output and
standard input so I wanted you to see
the difference okay now we started we're
kind of leading into like how do I write
stuff to a file and things like that but
the only thing you need to take away
from this right now is that standard
output is number one file descriptor and
standard error is number
two so what we said was by default
everything prints out to standard output
and so we said instead of printing to
standard output print to standard error
redirect standard output to standard
error and by doing that it didn't impact
so we were still able to capture the
output of standard output and use it
otherwise as you saw you would have get
you would get this problem where it
would put the prompt because the prompt
was not print to standard it was print
to standard output and you I don't know
if you noticed but it didn't even put
the prompt for us it didn't even show us
the prompt right so this is kind of an
interesting little trick and I I feel
like it does kind of give a sense of
like how to use um how to use standard
input and out and errror for for for fun
um so you could say you know hello you
can say uh Rob right and let's let's
actually change a little bit now there
there is kind of a quirk here is still
happening so you can see that the prompt
itself um is it's got a problem right
why is it still
colored well it's because we only
redirected one of our things we need to
re this redirect this thing too now
right that's why hello is gold so if we
do that this should take care of it
should let's try yep there we go Okay so
the thing that's really cool about this
is you can now inline prompting for
different things as you're going along
and um that's kind of fun for when
you're making all kind of thing so this
is the actual output right uh actual
output suitable for
consumption uh
yeah tell tell so why didn't it show in
ER just now I got a hiccup yeah there's
uh there's been some frame drops a
little bit
um uh send to stud
eror uh send to stud
erir
um
capture stud in owner f s yeah good good
good
good and then say actual output C for
consumption Okay so
is it prompting absolutely an an pattern
this we're just making they're just
learning about stuff yeah bash script
should never prompt right you should
never this is where I you know what
cookie you're right but this is where I
have trouble right because a lot of the
the ways I've been teaching this stuff
like like we're going to do magic
eightball interactivity and a show some
somebody in YouTube or and twitch is
rightly saying that you should never
prompt in any bash script because what
you're doing is you're forcing your
program to block and so what that means
is that if you combine your script with
another script uh in some form of
automation that it'll block and it'll
stop working unless you send you it's
it's waiting around for somebody to
interact with it and the best practice
which is absolutely true is to not ever
ask for interactive input the best
practice is to require environment
variables to be set to run and if they
aren't set to promp for them or to do a
prompting you know what I'm saying so
you know that is a very fair thing to
say um that said however on occasion it
is it is fun to make an interactive
script so we're about we're going to
make a magic eightball program and
that's what we're kind of leading up to
and you know if you if you have an
interactive terminal UI program then you
know that's a different context it's a
different use case and and that is
largely where most of my content has has
been evolving around interactive Story
game thing like that but if you're
writing if you're writing a script for
production that needs to run you should
never interactively ask for something um
you don't understand how it helped all
right well let me show you what happens
if we don't do it I want you to watch
the difference okay so if
we if we change this let's like take our
program
here um all right let's comment this one
out
CMT and let's run it this way
now I'm going to get rid of the
redirection and I want you to look
really closely at what's happening it's
really important that you understand
what's happening because if you don't
understand you won't understand the the
the nature of of um capture things all
right so look at this program so what is
this programming doing right it's it's
saying hello but and it's using a
variable but that variable is an it's
it's kind of a weird thing right but I'm
doing it kind of I just to illustrate a
point so when this runs it's going to
block now I could have put name
here
yeah g GH prompts for sure yeah there
there are many cases where prompting is
totally fine so yeah it's it's the right
it's you just just know that just
depends on how your thing is pro
planning on being used right but in this
case I put prompt right so I tape Rob
here all right what did it
do all right so I I want you to look at
that output really carefully and then I
want you to say I want you to see what
what's going on
okay do you see it do you see what it
did so it
took it took the output so we printed
out this PR here right right whoops
right here we printed out this prompt
right
here and what
happened it printed
out and it got it got added
into it got echoed out and then it got
lighted now why was that the reason is
because the
prompt as well as the reset and this
line right here here that Echoes the
input all got printed out to the same
place standard
output I don't know if you noticed but
when I ran this it didn't even show me
the
prompt why it didn't show me the prompt
because it was waiting around to give me
the the
output so again when you put when you
call a program like this what it does is
it captures the output of the program
and replaces it and uses it as a
variable so you know if if we had put
the date there right so let me give you
let's revisit this a little bit if I had
said
um Echo uh today is date
right so that that that takes that takes
the output of
date and it replaces it as if it had
been assigned to a variable right there
okay but think now now think about what
prompt was doing prompt is trying to
replace this thing with its
output but it the output is it's got two
outputs it's got the output that weights
around for me to type something in and
it's also got the output that is the
actual thing I typed in and that's and
that's the problem the problem is that
that's why we get the magenta prompt as
if I had you know
made it a part of the string and so what
we're doing normally redirecting
standard a and standard out are not this
is not what it's done it's usually
because you don't want to see all the
error messages but I if you can get your
head around this and it might take you a
while but if you can get your head
around what is actually happening there
you will perfectly understand standard
error and standard out and standard
input redirection because all three of
them are there all three streams are in
that example
can you name
them all right so let's go back and name
them right this is kind of a good good
way to quiz
yourself what my friends what is this
here okay
so PR what is where is that going where
is that prompt that magenta prompt and
that little prompt thing what stream is
that going to what stream of data is
that going
to standard output
right what
stream is being read to go into the
line standard
input okay this is reading from standard
input the input is what people are
typing in what's going into the
program uh yeah yeah read standard up
okay and then and then this one Echo
dasn that just says don't put a line
return reset so this is sending a
special ANC Escape for resetting the
color to what
stream standard
output and then this echo echo the line
that we read from standard input we're
going to Echo it back out and we're
going to print it to Echo it to standard
output so we have one line of standard
input whatever we typed in and we have
oneish
lines and two lines of
output and that's what we ended up
seeing here hello
comma now the reason the hello actually
comes from the echo so prompt so prompt
actually has this has one line of text
that comes out of it this right so what
we're going to do here is we're going to
cheat and we're going to use standard
error which is designed to be throwaway
standard error is is designed to display
to the user but to have it be disposable
it's supposed to be
disposable so so now what we can do is
we can say I want to make this
disposable and we can say I want to
redirect uh the default to uh to
two and there's actually two ways of
doing this you could do it either like
that or you can do it like that either
way now quite
honestly usually when you're redirector
output like this you're redirecting it
to to
devnull which says don't print it out at
all nothing gets to see it right so and
zero is is in standard input one is
standard output and two is standard
error and those numbers are always the
same those are the same file descriptor
numbers so so you can actually make new
file descriptors I found out a while ago
um but we're not going to get into that
right now so we're going to redirect our
output to standard error instead and
then we're going to do it right here now
is that is that a beginner content I
don't know probably not but I do feel
like it's it's a pretty solid way to to
illustrate what the three streams are
doing because you know hello
there uh
prompts uh you
know uh Rob right now let's since we're
at this
um let's go files and streams work yeah
so um you know we we only really want to
think about those three streams right
now because they're going to pop up all
the time you're going to use if you're
using the terminal you're using those
three streams constantly so wouldn't it
be great if we could put something else
here instead of it just being the
prompt um what if we could also let's go
back to this
one whoopsie
[Music]
um what am I doing
AP uh you same
team
Rob all right there we go so what if
what if we wanted to actually say
something more
right uh let's say I want to say
something more let's
say I want there to be more information
here so they could
say um you know we could actually print
the prompt so we could
say
um uh let's
say text how about that text equals and
we're going to put everything from the
command line into a variable and we're
going to say and now we're going to
print it out so we can say
text right now we should probably do
this
instead should probably do we want it to
be on the same
line yeah let's do that let's do that
let's have it be on the same line S here
instead of having
magenta then we're going to have a text
now I could have just
done this
right so um you
know yeah let's uh let's actually do
this
instead yeah and it could be empty so
let's try that now let's do our thing
again hello there okay oops okay see I
said prompt but let's let's actually
change it see
prompt uh name
name now it says your name like what's
your name
right uh rob you could say
prompt uh what is your
name and it'll do it okay if you feel if
you make it if you feel makes you feel
safer you can put that you can put
quotes around that you know you could
say this you could say what is your name
on and here's where it gets
funny um
what is your name on this date you can
actually Nest these
things
Rob I know there's a lot happening there
kind of on
purpose because I want to this is this
is where the power starts to come in of
shell because you can you can intermix
things with each other and we haven't
even gotten to pipes yet right we
haven't even gotten to pipes yet so you
actually make these like things that are
composed of other things and that's
where things get really really powerful
um so you could have it be you know you
could have you could have it instead of
being date you could have it be you know
um you know you could you could have it
be anything you could you could have it
be you could have it be literally
anything and you can have it be like
um you know yeah I mean you could get
rid of prompt you could have it be BC
well anyway I'm getting h of myself so
anyway prompt from all right so hello
there Rob now what what we did is we
just made ourselves a reusable prompt
command now that that command can be
used any place that we ever want to
prompt for input ever so from now on in
perpetuity in the Unix velosophy I now
have a command that I can execute and I
can make it do anything I can run it by
itself uh I prompt uh what do you want
to do now a question mark it's like
hello you know we should probably get
rid of the question mark in the prompt
because it might not be a question it
might be a might be a action or
something right so let's get rid of that
oops let's get rid of that part and then
so what do you want to do
now right let's put uh a space after it
that's probably
wise Pro what do you want to do
now uh whatever right now you could
actually put um like like if you want to
get crazy with the color the thing of it
is we're not going to have to do this
again we only rot it once and then we're
going to reuse it all the time so you
can like really get nice you know fixing
it up and stuff let's actually make it a
different color shall we let's make it
um black which is not is
prominent I think black is is
zero and we could actually just use the
numbers if we wanted
but the V the videos aren't laggy the
the the videos aren't
lagging
yep there hasn't been any lag so
far in this
video
yeah we already redid we just re you
weren't here when we redid the whole
thing I'm not going to talk about it
we'll talk about it during the break I
re I reset my entire modem and I ordered
a new one so if it's still lagging I
can't help you guys it's Upstream 100%
Upstream yep okay so there's a there's a
prompt in there it's kind of kind of
hard to see but it is it is
there you know what we could probably
just remove it completely how about that
we really don't need
it we don't need it let's just get rid
of it because we can put whatever the
you know
hello you know what I'm saying so prompt
blah blah blah now we have this nice
happy thing that we can use all the time
when we want to and we can do some other
coding with it okay so that that was the
point of that the point of this is that
we are doing this the unix's way we're
making one command that does something
useful that we can regroup together and
combine with other things and I started
doing this by putting them into
functions and that's very much the
python or JavaScript way but it's
definitely not the Unix way the Unix way
is to make them all into commands that
then can be composed together in all
kinds of creative interesting ways um
that are not dependent on everything
being in the same file so this is very
much a different approach to it from you
know python or JavaScript or node or
whatever and that and that's those those
tools would have you you know want to
use one of their specific plugins or or
function libraries or something because
you'd have to that when we get coding in
go you'll see that that's a thing in go
it's more about you know making a bunch
of re reusable function library or
procedure Library than it is about
creating a bunch of independent commands
that can do really amazing cool things
so but I really want you to start down
this path properly with bash by by
making you know one or two command you
know commands that do one thing really
well all right so what do we got now
we're we're now on to the next thing and
we have another 30 minutes okay so so
far we haven't made anything really
substantial but we've learned about
variables we've learned about you know
uh we've learned a little bit about
conditions um we we started to learn
about conditions but we kind of
sidetracked on that with case um so now
what what's the next thing we're going
to make um we've also talked about
functions but instead of talking about
functions of procedures what I'd rather
you take away from this is I'm going to
make a command that does something
that's way more valuable for bash than
understanding how to make a function and
I hope I haven't beat that to death but
it's it's it's critical that you
understand why that's a significant
difference all right so you can kind of
if you've done programming before you
can think of these commands as
procedures or functions wherever you
want um because they're essentially the
same thing all right so now it's time to
start doing something more fun let's
let's actually take our Randomness we
have our random color uh we've got a
whole bunch of really great things that
we've done so we can start assembling
our things together to make something
interesting uh or you know just fun for
today and so so what could we do let's
let's do Nan cat we already did that
let's make a a very stupid simple
program that does n Cat and if you know
at nine cat it just continues to repeat
things okay let's actually make one so
again the point of this is repeating the
steps over and over again so they stick
in your head um uh chat from let's see
is it streamlabs comment on Twitch chat
from aric shrub no it's a it's a bot
it's a thing that's copying it over it's
a bot that's copying over yeah
streamlabs is coming from my bot okay so
it's coming from my my my bot yeah all
right so here here we go we're going to
go ahead and now we're going to we're
going to put some stuff together so
let's just make something silly wouldn't
it be fun if we could make that repeat
right so you can actually start playing
around with this what if we did this
Rand Color Fun what if we did this while
true do that uh sleep for
0.1 and then do it again so now you know
it's a thing right
that's kind of cool what if we did
instead of Rand color fun um you know
it's actually not putting it on its own
line it's like you know uh but like what
if we did that and we wanted it to be on
the same line let's see if we can do
that
Echo thisn I'm going to see if this will
fix it for us um yep there we go so the
thing to take away from this is that
when you make um this is actually
happens for automatically when when you
put a command inside of a parameter you
know a variable a sub command shell like
we did um it actually takes the line
return off of the end for you
automatically so that's what we just did
with that so what if we could put that
into a program my friends this is what
this is the best part about shell I can
actually I'm going to use t-mo and I'm
going to take that one liner that I just
wrote and I'm going to put this thing
inside have a script so I'm going to
open up a
script uh we'll call it
nen and I'm going to paste it
oops paste it in God Rob place it in
here give it a shebang line and honestly
we don't need more than bsh in this so
we're fine bsh and B Bash bin bash if
you can but in this case there's nothing
new going on here so you know we don't
have we have our random colors already
covered by bash so we don't need
anything more we can just use regular
old b h and we can do the echo right
here put our sleep in here and quote
this to prevent word splitting okay so
let's go ahead and do that and we can
say function find code going to say
Yen and uh posi Echo flags are undefined
oh I they remember I was telling you
about Echo doesn't do sh this is good
this is good you see how shell Che
caught it for me because it saw the bsh
is posic shell which is a limited shell
version it's not bash so I can either
change to bash and get unnecessary
overhead or I can keep it in in bsh and
I can change it to print F okay but then
it's going to complain because it's like
you can't do substitution yeah so so
then we do this we do s and make it
happy and we put this over here and call
it a day so again the the percent s is
where the thing gets substituted uh and
then that that's 100% perfect shell
script we talked a little bit about bash
versus POS this is one of those cases
but you see what I'm saying by by by
making them composing them into single
individual commands the commands that
need bash can use bash the commands that
don't need bash don't necessarily have
to use bash and while it's nice to
default A bash it is kind of nice to do
that there's been a there's been a
little bit of video video stuttering
yeah uh it's no longer happening only
about three times okay yeah we just we
just we're having we're having packet
loss right now big time too
I I don't know what's going on with that
I can't I can't solve it so anyway so
now we're going to go ahead and do it
again so okay I can't run it though why
why can't I run it you guys
remember why can't I run
it what's wrong with that now why won't
it
run we're having massive packet
loss yeah I don't I don't think the
packet loss is because of me
now I
don't yeah yeah we need schmocks right
we need permissions right so we need
schmod plus X schmocks or schmod plus X
which is just an alias it's just hard to
type and so I don't type it very
much I am not uploading anymore now
uploading is over
with yep that's done
all right so nen and now we can run it
but you see how I didn't have to do do
slash why didn't I have to do slash that
time we already talked about this this
is I think this a video you miss
YouTuber but that that is what we did
when we figured out path we spend an
hour talking about path and how to do it
safely um and then so we're going to do
nen and you can actually adjust the
speed on
that by setting it up to a bit faster we
could say
005 or you could
say um you know what's funny you can do
is you can actually keep it in the same
directory in the same directory as the
script yes but I we've also added this
to the path already we did that earlier
so just want to let people
know so there we go
I mean that's pretty fast it's almost
like a terminal
tester yeah it's kind of garish but
whatever
[Music]
um
three yeah
so if Boulder is in my path we added we
added we did that earlier
yep we we I showed you guys how to do
this and it's in it's in my
bachy I I showed you guys how to how to
add it to the pat there is we did we did
the thing with path and we talked about
how don't screw your path up Etc so we
did we covered that already so that's it
so let's let's continue down this path
L um we just we're just doing a loop so
the first Loop to know is while and what
wild does is when this condition is true
it continues it and there's two key
wordss true and false that you can use
um as we're done here true is obviously
always true so this is an infinite Loop
um but now there are other conditions
where it might not be true right so you
might want a condition where it's true
and one where it wouldn't be right so
you can already think of some things you
could probably do here and I'm those of
you know about for Loops just please
stay tight for a second I have a plan
okay so let let's say we only want to do
it 10 times intuitively what would you
do intuitively you'd say well okay we
need a variable so let's add one so we
say n so they say n equals or you could
say count if you want it's up to you say
count equals uh we'll start with zero
right it says count as unused verify as
a thing okay so let me say well why well
count is you know less than and this is
where the difference between bash and
shell come in start to get interesting
so while count is less than
10 there's a much easier way to do this
but I just want to show you this so
while can is less than 10 keep doing it
you can only tell Shel Che is yelling at
me it's like what the hell are you doing
right so it's like this is a this is a
file redirection this is not less than
was it supposed to be something
else because there's no such thing as
that so if we're using posix
shell um then we need to do this we
could say less than 10 all right but
then it's like hm is that a thing right
well is it still going to go forever
account appears to be unused well it's
not a variable you need to make it a
variable okay now it's a variable right
so well count is less than 10 and
unfortunately I'm going to have to show
you many many ways to do conditions
because you're going to encounter these
all over you're going to see these kind
of conditional things where the operator
is the less is less than is a dash and
other ones where it's an actual less
than and I want to show you both because
you're going to see both a lot so if so
we're going to run Y what is it going to
do and not going to do anything because
why it's like there's no such command is
that like what the hell are you talking
about
um wait
what line four 0 1 2 3 four all right so
line four there's no such thing as count
because it's not a count right all right
so this is a condition so we actually
have to put the condition inside of
something else I'm going to do something
that might be a little strange to some
of you who've done shell in the past but
watch this all right so if I do this it
works and I really I'm doing this on
purpose I'm deliberately doing a bunch
of sh people just like lost their minds
because they're like why are you showing
them that
because this is what's actually
happening when you do shell when you do
shell you're actually running a command
in in posic shill you are running a
command and hear me out this is the way
to learn this okay so it said that there
was no command B where it said there's
no such command as
count no it's fine do you see any double
brackets or single brackets there are
none and it works why why does it work I
really really really want you to process
this if you understand why this works
you'll understand shell better than 80%
of the veterans that I've worked with in
the in the professional
World it doesn't have to have a bracket
why because the condition itself is the
execution of a
command my
friends in a sense actually test doesn't
even work this is this is going to blow
your mind if you don't know this already
in all modern shells but in the original
shell this you remember we talked about
things being passed into you know all
the the
arguments so what this is doing is it's
running this this is the program and
each of these is an option that's passed
into the
program that's why it's DLT
the reason that it's DLT and it's- GT is
because those are options to the test
program I guarantee you I guarantee you
there are veterans that you will run
into who have no idea what I'm talking
about the DLT is an option to the test
program and this the count variable is
the first argument to the test program
and the last argument to the test
program in this casee is the
10 okay so what is that actually
doing so what that's doing is it's
passing it's running a
program okay and the and the return
value of the test program in this case
continues to be we haven't got to return
values yet 0 and one but it's in this
case it's zero every time until it's not
so what you'll see people write and and
this is what you'll see people write but
I want you to understand it's the same
thing why is that important because when
you're looking up how to do
conditions this is how you do it man
test this will tell you everything you
need to
know the test program is what you're
running now is it true that modern
shells have built this into the shell
itself and they're now built-in yes
that's true but it's really important
that you want understand the origins of
this because you will find Shell systems
where this is all there is and it's
super important that you understand that
this is a separate command test is a
separate command and this this left
bracket is actually a command you can
actually find it with the path command
it'll show you right where it
lives now there are so many people that
do not know
that yeah the required space after the
bracket was so word for me but that is
why and that is why cookie that is why
that is why I'm telling you about this
the reason for the really weird ha to
has a space in between them all the
reason for that is because as we just
saw every one of those things is an
argument to the test command and the
only way to separate arguments passed
into the test command is with a space
that is why a space is required
I guarantee you 90% of the admins have
no idea why spaces are required they
think this is a stupid syntax why is
this that way now you
know a lot of people do not know this a
lot of people and you know it now you
know it um even if you don't care right
you're just like I'm going to put a
space there because someone told me to
now you know why you can explain why to
somebody
else the thing that's really crazy about
this is that the second
bracket is an argument that's passed to
the test
command how's that to blow your
mind the this the the closing
bracket is not part of bash or shell it
is it is an argument it's an it's an
argument it's one of the arguments so so
the first bracket is the command and the
last bracket is an argument that
signifies the end of the arguments
that is why by the way this is also why
you get these really really really weird
it can't um I don't think it can be can
it be I don't can it be can it be
omitted I think you well I mean you can
definitely admit it with the test
command I that that'd be
interesting is that a
thing expect test to end here don't
rap I don't I don't think I don't think
this is going to work this is super
curious yeah it doesn't
work yeah so no if you're going to use
that format it it doesn't like it so but
you can use test and let me tell you
something a lot of times code is much
easier to write with the test keyword
than it is with the brackets and it's
easier to read too particularly when you
start getting into short circuit logic
which we haven't done yet when you start
doing short circuit logic not using
brackets double or single starts to make
a lot of sense and it's it's a lot
easier to read so I'm just letting you
know that that's the
thing after the second bracket will be
another it be another argument yeah so
now you can so having said that you can
replace this this is posic shell so
we're using single brackets you can't
use double brackets and posic Shell by
the way what is that that's a mistake
why because it has to be an
argument again I swi gears on you I'm
now using posic shell instead of Bash
that's why there's single brackets using
single brackets in bash is a mistake
absolutely it's a total mistake
unnecessarily Rose uh completely
unsecure because of expansion which we
haven't got into if you're doing bash
use double bracket or test if you're
using posic shell use test or single
single bracket don't use single brackets
in your bash please just promise me you
won't there's no need for it so um so
now you know the difference between the
two shells so you've got this is the
same this is exactly the same as the
other one exactly the same okay now the
difference here is and I'm going to I'm
going to make this bash for one second
because I want you to see the difference
but when you make this into a bash
script and it could be bin bash which is
version 3 of bash if you want for now
that code will work that code will work
no
problem um but
but this will
also work which is safer
and um what else um and this will also
work I
think oh
wait oh no wa I mean we have to do the
math thing yeah I forgot about that yeah
never mind I guess I guess that's the
only one for that yeah I I I I'm
mistaking something you could do this
instead yeah so this does mathematical
comparison
and when you do this you don't need this
and now you don't need the space which I
just blew somebody's mind all that
I was just saying about putting a space
there when you're doing math it doesn't
matter when you're doing mathematical
comparisons it doesn't matter in fact it
it'll even you don't you don't even need
the the the the dollar
anymore okay so so that if you're if
you're doing a mathematical thing you
can use the two instead of two brackets
you can use
I don't think this is a shill thing
honestly I it's really not math and Bash
and math and puic shell are totally
different and I really don't want to go
down that rabit hole right now but I'm
going to try it anyway yeah you can't do
it yeah there's there's no such
thing
um yeah so only bash has got the
mathematical operator which is why you
would want to do that okay so you know
and um to tell you the truth you're
going to want the mathematical
operators um
this is this is kind of an interesting
point at which you know like do
we oh is it is it two is it two from PX
it it has to have it all right let's
try remove the
dollar to avoid what what the hell is
this about shell check is like giving me
all kinds of
stuff oh that what the hell is
that what the heck is
that that's what Shi check tells to do I
no wonder I've never used that I don't
use that I don't like this is why I use
bash because it's like we start out
learning bash and we're going to keep
learning Bash from now on but um the
second bucket becomes a close argument
for they won't get past those argument
yes
so apparently in posic Shell the only
time you can use this syntax is as an
assignment and you know so we're going
back to bash
uh we can user B user b bash this is
going to be slower
but um I I we we're learning bash is the
first thing but if you want to go back
and look at all the other stuff you can
uh now you can either do this or you can
use the test command or you can just use
math the math is a lot faster because it
doesn't I mean this I'm catching myself
because both of these shells no longer
shell out to run the test they used to
um um so anyway so there you go there's
your count like 10 and that's then you
got your your thing right okay but how
do we how do we increment it how do we
increment it
so um so let's actually increment it so
we need to make it bigger so we're going
to say count equals count +
one and that's a thing all right so but
I'm going to comment it out because
that's kind of a waste you can do plus
equal
1 which is also a thing that says add
one to
it right or you can say
Plus+ which says just add one to it
they're all the same all three of those
are the same so put those in your
notes okay now let's run it now we run
yankat and it just ran 10 of them and
stopped okay it R them really fast but
it stopped and only ran 10 of them all
right now we're going to we're going to
wrap up the today with one more version
of this okay and I want you to see this
all
right um this is an IT initialize a
variable
right all right this
here is
check check check the variable
uh uh check the variable against a
condition uh okay and then this down
here is the change change the variable
in some way you probably know where I'm
going with this all right this is really
really important I want you to see this
what we're
doing okay so and we're the next thing
we're going to finish is the end
of looping and the last thing we got to
do is functional recursion but we'll
wait on that till another till later so
in fact we're probably not going to do
functional recurs until we get into go
there's no reason to do it in Shell at
all um all right so what what have we
done
here now wouldn't it be great if we
could put all of that into one
line if we can put all of that
information all of that stuff into one
line instead of having it spread out all
over like especially like what even this
wild Loop right in this while down at
far far at the bottom it could be off on
the page it's like I can't remember what
the condition is and stuff would it be
great if it were all on one line well
every programming language on the planet
pretty much supports that alternative
syntax so what I'm going to do here is
I'm going to comment this call all this
code out using a technique which is kind
of fun we're just going to do this right
I'm going to put an eom down here now
what did I just do make sure you put
that in your notes I just block
commented out that entire
thing that code is not going to run
anymore that's why it's green you can
use that for comments you can use that
for commenting out huge blocks of code
uh a lot of people don't know that you'd
be surprised how many how many Unix
people do not know that you can do that
they they will come up with all kinds of
convoluted things and they will put like
you know they'll create you they'll do
visual mode and they'll you know put
comments on the whole thing if you just
want to turn off a whole section of code
and shell
that's what you do I just did it all I
did is I turned it into a big old string
and I told it to do nothing with the
string and that's what this
is
um will Rand Color Run yes absolutely
now this is off no no it won't run nope
here watch so let's try it
see I mean actually I think it does run
good point you know I think it does
actually run because this is uh you know
what we can do
this would be even better how about that
and you know what that's a good catch
good catch because it was embedded so it
actually would have run yeah good catch
good catch that was really good thank
you for that um so and you know what we
kind of got a hint about that because it
was still
showing so you know color matters every
anybody who ever tells you color is
juvenile that's a direct quote from
somebody color in this case shows you
that hey something's not going why is
that okay that we're going to get to
this later but the that's because you
remember how you can have strings with
either double quotes or single quotes
when you have double quotes it doesn't
do the things inside I'm sorry when you
have single quotes it doesn't when you
have double it does so it's still trying
to do the thing there so I think so
we're going to go ahead and put double
quotes around it just to be clear I mean
single quotes and that's going to say
hey I want I want all this stuff to be
single quoted instead of double quoted
uh there's one other thing you can do
here you can put a dash which we'll get
to later but that actually automatically
indents everything thing and I don't
know if you saw but it automatically did
it Prem me it indents it with tabs which
are the standard Tabs are the standard
in Shell initial Tabs are the standard
if you using anything else you're using
non-standard stuff I'm I'm not making
the rules that's the official that's why
that's why sh fmt reformats with tabs
and you can fight me till the grave on
that I don't give a that is exactly
way it is if you're using anything but
tabs you're not writing Shell Code
you're not because this Dash only works
with Taps it doesn't work with
spaces I didn't make the rule I'm just
reporting you to the rule okay so there
you
go you know how many people don't know
that Pros that have been doing this for
40 years they will put spaces in here
and think it's totally fine and they'll
get mad at you for putting tabs there
they'll yell at you for putting tabs
there and you like really because the
shmt tool uses
tabs I was one of them
I got mad at a newbie on our team I was
like why are you putting tabs in there
he say well that's what sfmt does I'm
like what he goes yeah it must be the
standard or something and then I I
looked into the dash and I was like I
don't I know what's standard but I hate
it I was wrong and he's like no you
don't need to do that don't do that ever
again and I'm like I never have so and
besides if you're Auto formatting who
cares who cares if you're doing sh fmt
and it's automatically formatting if you
don't know how to do that by the way
it's all in my
MC uh programming with syntax
highlighting seems Mass
it's not masochistic it's more
efficient yeah not having syntax
highlighting is dangerous in 2024 and
all of the people who say that all they
need is black and
white the only proper response to that
is okay
Boomer because I have caught
misconfigurations in production SSH
configurations because I had color and
the guy who set it up who made the
production mist mistake that almost took
down our system didn't have color and he
didn't see his mistake had he had a
syntax highlighter he would have seen it
in production in operations so I I don't
want to hear that anymore if you're
going to push black and white terminal
on me that that's all that anybody ever
needs great you do you but it's stupid
okay so anyway here we
go oh did you say without oh I'm sorry
then thank God it's not not there
programming without synx
highlighting I didn't mean to go off on
you I I didn't read properly all right
actually I did I'm glad you heard that
so anyway anyway in 2024 not having C
color and saying it's juvenile that's a
direct quote by the way from a very
important person who created Unix and
and
stuff you know whatever you they're
they're fine um anyway let's do
something more productive um we're about
done with this we're about done on an
hour here and what I was trying to get
to you is to this part this is the main
part we can rewrite this in the same
code in one line in fact we don't even
really need to change all of this but
instead of this okay we're going to do
oh by the way here's another trick you
ever you ever want your your your shell
check to shut up just put a noop in
there a common noop that's what that or
a colon noop okay okay there is no count
okay let's refer to the count let's
change it from a while to a four and now
we're going to say while count count
equals 0
semicolon and then and we're going to
have count
Plus+ oh my Lord what just happened
right and now we can take the rest of
our code and put it in here put two
those two things in
there um you know and and that's
it now I had some other code in there
for fun but so here we go that's it now
that does exactly the same thing
so and we run
it 10 10 repeats there is one other way
to do this that I'm going to show you
before we leave um that's a bash only
way and but what I want you to see here
is this this is the takeaway from this
init check change init check change and
it check change say it 10 times and it
check change and it check change and it
check change you know how many times in
my career I forgotten the order of
these the most common mistake I make and
I'm a little dyslexic I still make this
mistake is I will I I can't tell you how
many minutes maybe even hours that I
have lost with some stupid mistake
because I put the change in the middle
instead of the
check I do this all the time and I'm I'm
going to blame my D partial dyslexia on
this but I will put I will do basically
and it check change and it check change
if the middle one is the check the
middle one is the check and the last one
is the change and I have swapped those
so many times and it runs it runs but it
doesn't do what I think it's going to do
and I'm like oh my God all right but the
takeaway from this is that these two
Loops this what these are called These
are called loops these two Loops are
identical they're identical they do
exactly the same thing so much so that
the go language doesn't have a while
keyword it only has a four keyword
because Rob Pike Rob Pike's like why do
we need that it's just wasting time on
the compiler I don't need it I can just
use four
instead and we're we're going to get to
that we're going to code and go later
but for right now I want you to see this
so you've got a while loop or you've got
a for Loop right you can do both of them
and by the way this is the same for
python Ruby Pearl JavaScript rust
anything Java they all have the same
idea right and again and by the way it
doesn't have to be numbers AIT check
change initial
initialization checking for a true
condition and it it doesn't have to be a
number comparison it could be anything
you could check to see whether a
variable had something in it or not and
then the change what is changing is in
this case it's always you know adding a
Plus on there um in C plus plus code and
other things like that you'll see the
use of plus plus or minus minus minus
minus decrements it so you'll see this
too you could do this exact same thing
like this and you could say is greater
than
zero and and then you could do count
minus minus if you
prefer it's up to you it's the same
thing same exact thing okay so and and
you can do it by you can jump by two if
you want you can say if you if you want
to do evens and odds uh you can actually
do modu 2 to say I only want the to
print on the odds um you know you can
you can you could do the same thing you
could let's say you had like 10 lines
and you were going through all the lines
you could print only the even ones by
making the condition module two or
something or actually having the account
condition be whatever add one to it and
then the condition would be mod two and
then it would only print the evens or
only print the odds there's there's just
you know a myriad of of possibilities
here this is why you're learning loops
like this there is one last Loop before
I'm going to end this video and this
Loop is exactly the same as this Loop
um and I'm going to uh well I mean I
could just CMT that that's fine too I
don't care see I'm kind of any either
way is fine with me there okay so this
is a bash only thing a lot of people
don't know this and it is really really
useful especially from the command line
so you can do this zero let's say I want
to do it 10 times so I want it from 1 to
10 or you can do from 0 to 10 right R to
do Echo uh let's do I let's do or I in 1
to 10 we're going to get there's another
another thing for Loops can do is they
can iterate over the things that are
there and that's going to happen later
we're going to have to do that probably
next but what we can do here uh done so
uh yeah so this is just going to you
know out output the
number and this is of course this is an
an Yan
cat but it'll do 1 to 10 and um so so
here we go you can do four of that so
actually if you want to do that you
could do one and then you could do
Yen right you do one and in y and you
can say oopsie
wait what am I doing I'm I'm that's I
just recursed myself that was horrible
Rand
color I did recursion on myself there
yeah bad bad me all right so do that
there you go there's 10
yans
uh
yeah uh I like the the 4X and command
looping that's also a thing yep yep but
that's uh back tick whether it's back
tick or that
yeah if okay so there's there's another
way to do this so the posic show way of
doing this uh is
this so you can put all these in there
well let's do this turn this one
on uh if if you want to know how to do
the incremental number thing in posic
Shell you use the
sequence uh this is a subshell but you
do suq to
10 and that will give you 10 from 10 to
whatever um same exact oh my god did you
see it fixed my thing it got rid of my
back
ticks sh fmt replaced my back
ticks these are all getting recorded
yeah so it replaced my back ticks these
are the same this is posix only
so uh if you've only got posix shell
then that's the thing this is Bash
only uh bash
only POS sh
uh so you know there's lots of things
you can do here or you can do the like
the really long winded one uh and
there's you know lots of lots of
different ways to Loop here um uh we're
going to do
iteration iteration is kind of a
different thing than numeric counting so
we're going to save iteration until we
can go over um you know lists and stuff
and that'll probably be the next video
uh so we'll do another video after this
um but but yeah so this is all saved
remember how to save it let's go ahead
and save it get get add dog commit DM
add uh
Yen uh prompt
Etc and then we want get push so that's
how you save your code if you haven't
done it um GH repo view-- web to open it
up and you can share it um if you want
to go arix robab sample for now I
probably will archive it which means it
won't appear in my list even though
you'll be able to get to it if you know
that address so so I'll I'll leave that
there for a while and and you can go you
can go look at that um but WIP is not
home yet so I'm going to go ahead and
make yet another video and we're going
to finish um we're going to finish the
uh the looping and iterations over over
um over things now we have indirectly
covered types and so there's two more
complex types to cover um and after we
cover that you pretty much know
everything uh everything that's
necessary to to make a bash RC really
amazing and um and then the final video
will be us going through the The Bash uh
The Bash RC file itself and then you can
see all the stuff that's in there um we
do have to do complex conditions which
we have not done yet we have not
combined more than one condition yet we
have not done short circuit logic we
have not done um um you know that's
that's it and then of course the the
iteration stuff those those will be the
looping techniques that we have to use
and honestly that is it that is it we've
done you you know how to do math you
know you know how to do recursion you
know do most most everything and that
that's enough that's enough for pretty
much any Dynamic configuration uh we're
not do a truth table now so so you know
whether you're doing a configuration in
Lua or you're doing a configuration in
uh per neam or westerm are you doing
like a bachelor C configuration or
anything most of the things that have
Dynamic configuration of any kind limit
themselves to the basic logic of
procedural programming that we've been
doing so far this is why it's such an
essential for the beginners to learn
this stuff because not only is it what
you do every day when on your command
line but it's also the same idea in
other Dynamic configurations um and
after we finish the bash RC thing the
next thing we're going to do after that
is going to be Json with JQ and yaml
with yq and potentially toml and talk
about that and then the next thing after
that will be go and that's going to
cover it for this holiday boost all
right so I'm going to take another break
I'll talk to you in a bit if you want to
hang out with me um I'm just going to
keep knocking these out the reason I
want these to be around is I want people
for the next several months to be able
to go redo these and feel like they're
getting something out of them while I'm
working on the booking thing talk to in
a bit